# PRASHANT KUMAR

### **CONTACT**

Address: Faridabad, India 121013

Phone: +917011284601

Email: prashantjha076@gmail.com

**WWW:** Bold Profile

#### **SKILLS**

- Adaptability:
- Problem-Solving
- Customer Service
- Attention to Detail
- Collaboration
- Cultural Sensitivity
- Project Management
- US and Global Immigration Laws and Regulations
- Relocation Management
- Assignment Management
- Cost Estimation
- Cross-Cultural Communication
- Policy Development and Compliance
- Vendor Management
- · Data Analysis and Reporting

### **LANGUAGES**

Hindi

Maithili

**English** 

### PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Organized and dependable Immigration & Mobility specialist with an overall 8 years of experience which is combined with Immigration & Sales background, out of which 5.5 years have been in Mobility and Immigration background in corporate office settings, who continually maintains a positive attitude while interacting with demanding clients. Successful at managing multiple priorities with a willingness to take on added responsibilities to meet team goals. Have a solid understanding of visa requirements and other issues for international personnel assignments. Have expert-level knowledge of all issues and global mission policies and procedures. Possesses a Bachelor's Degree in English Literature and 5.5 years of Global Mobility/ Immigration Specialist experience.

#### **WORK HISTORY**

## **Global Mobility Advisor III- US Immigration,** 01/2023 to 01/2024 **LabCorp** - Bengaluru, India

- Reviewing and processing of incoming Global Mobility and Relocation provided invoices and liaison with Finance re payment/tracking of payment.
- Preparing documentation, assignment/ relocation letters, assignment notifications, cross charging forms, assignees expense claims forms, company letters for visa applications, etc.
- Calculating short term allowance and Cost of Living allowance.
- Maintain and manage US and Global immigration authorization employee lists
- Supporting Assignment management tool functionality and ensuring it serves its day-to-day purpose and that related databases remain accurate and up to date.
- Work with case managers to continuously review effectiveness of operational processes and make necessary improvements.
- Worked on cost estimations for long-term delegation and supported case managers globally with cost projections for long-term delegations.
- · Generation and review of assignment documentation.
- · Ensure workday records are updated correctly.
- Monitor and review US leaver reports for individuals on visas.
- · Ensure immigration trackers are complete.
- Maintain Global immigration mailboxes and answered basic queries.
- Coordinating with Immigration and relocation Vendors for timely case initiation and assessment updates, Relocation Vendors, HR Partners, HR Service Delivery Teams, Hiring Managers, Recruiters, etc to update them about assignees' cases and immigration-related queries.
- Manage approval process for upcoming visa expiries and liaise with external counsel to initiate extensions.
- Support end-to-end process for all domestic or international relocation and

Immigration cases.

- Prepare visa applications and extensions, preparation of Company data, audit our files, and compliance for North America, Canada, LATAM, and EMEA regions.
- Consult with HR partners, business leaders, and other relevant stakeholders on relocation proposals, providing guidance on immigration matters, cost analysis, and timeline estimates.
- Supported on global mobility projects as and whenever asked by management.
- Managed all immigration and relocation cases for international transferees and impacted new hires including securing work authorization, defining the relocation package, and confirming all necessary approvals.
- Work closely with external vendors to manage outsourced components of the process, including visa application, tax consultation, and escalations where needed.
- Support employees and managers through the relocation process, leveraging your expertise to answer questions and ensuring that all relevant stakeholders are kept informed of progress.
- Manage assignment changes or extensions, repatriation of returning transferees, or permanent localization in the host country.
- Monitor all costs associated with relocation and immigration processes to ensure that we operate within the established budget.
- Track all active mobility and immigration cases to ensure that local requirements are being met and that each case remains in compliance.
- Partner with stakeholders across HR, Legal, Finance, and Payroll to evolve and enhance our Global Mobility policies covering domestic and international relocation for new hires and internal transfers.
- Provide reporting and analytics to business leaders and stakeholders.
- Worked with the broader HR Operations team to ensure that new hire work authorization checks meet local country requirements (e.g., US I-9, UK Right to Work).
- Remain up to date with market trends, regulatory changes, and local laws that impact existing transferees or future employee movement.
- Provide training to HR team members, business leaders, and employees on the immigration landscape, mobility policy, and processes.
- Compiling immigration metrics and keeping the management abreast with the latest details.
- Review internal processes regularly to recommend enhancements; partner with the HR Technology and Operations teams to implement changes.

# **Assistant Manager- Immigration,** 07/2022 to 12/2022 **CovetIT Inc** - Hyderabad

- Execute on day-to-day administration of direct reports including leave management, workforce management etc
- Provide guidance, direction, and evaluation of the work of the associates, provide regular feedback on staff performance
- · Assist in the management of work through efficient utilization of staff
- Coach direct reports on how to conduct process improvement workshops
- Performs job performance evaluation by observing employees' daily job performance. Administer written employee performances annually (or mid-season)

•

- Coordinating with attorneys and law firms for H-1B Amendment, H-1B
   Extension, H-1B Transfer, H4 Dependents visa filing, H4 EAD filing,
   including preparation of supporting documents for PERM / I-140/ I-485.
   /dispatching documents and briefing the consultants on visa stamping
   process and brief them how to fill DS-160 form.
- Constantly communicate with employees on immigration and resolve queries.
- Prepare visa cancellations/ Revoke letters to USCIS and also Port of entry letters for consultants.
- Work with recruitment to gather immigration assessment data to counsel for new hires.
- Assist employees in H1-B stamping process by preparing documents, handing over
- Ensure employees are well prepared to face H1b/L1 visa interviews before the consulates along with complete and accurate documentation.
- Maintaining files for immigration cases such as Public Access Files (PAF) and PERM documents.
- Coordinating with attorneys for on time LCA filing for our employees.
- Developed loyal and highly satisfied customer base through proactive management of team customer service strategies.

## **Sr. Immigration Executive,** 09/2018 to 06/2022 **Compunnel** - Noida, India

- Preparing and Drafting H-1B Amendment, H-1B Extension, H-1B Transfer, H4
  Dependents visa filing, H4 EAD filing, including preparation of supporting
  documents for PERM / I-140/ I-485
- Maintain the Global immigration mailboxes and answer basic gueries
- Ensure signed letters are received from individuals and filed accordingly
- Perform other duties as assigned by management
- Maintain our employee data as required for compliance purposes
- Gather company and employee data for US petitions
- Set up Green Card advertising in our systems, collate candidate responses and provide to counsel
- Work with recruitment to gather immigration assessment data to counsel for new hires
- Assist employees in H1-B stamping process by preparing documents, handing over /dispatching documents and briefing the consultants on visa stamping process and brief them how to fill DS-160 form
- Ensure employees are well prepared to face H1b/L1 visa interviews before the consulates along with complete and accurate documentation
- Contacting USCIS for obtaining information on visa approval delay or any Typographical Errors in the legal documents by raising service requests
- Address all queries raised by USCIS and Consulates on immigration and nonimmigration petitions and visas on high priority
- Co-ordinate with employees on the GC processing, preparing the required paperwork and co-ordinate with the attorney about the same
- Briefing candidates on frequently asked questions at immigration offices in the US or the US Consulate in India as well as USCIS site audits
- Responding to the RFEs received various H1B petitions
- Update, maintain and share all relevant reports with management

- Share H1b approval notice, LCA, GC and other important documents with the HR team to keep an employee record on the server
- Maintaining files for immigration cases such as Public Access Files (PAF) and PERM documents.
- Illustrated green card and immigration processes and managed communication channels to provide high level of service and consultation to immigration inquiries.
- Maintained public access files to facilitate compliance, documentation and execution of immigration policies and procedures.
- Led and offered consultation and guidance to business units to support PERM process.

# Technical Sales Associate, 07/2016 to 10/2016 MK ( Hyperquality) - Gurgaon, HR

- Attended product-related technical shows and other activities to represent company products and services.
- Recommended and explained features and costs to help customers make educated buying decisions.
- Developed a robust pipeline of sales opportunities by maintaining accurate information in CRM.
- Engaged large and medium end-users to deliver the company's total value proposition to increase sales.
- selling software packages and resolving customers queries related to their Laptops, Desktops, etc.

### **EDUCATION**

**Bachelor Of Arts**: English (Hons), 06/2016 **Maharishi Dayanand University** - Rohtak, HR

**12th**, 06/2013 **ASVJ Sr. Sec School** - Delhi, DL

Percentage: 60%Board: CBSE

**10th**, 06/2011 **St. Xavier's High School** - Deoghar, JH

Percentage: 8.4 CGPABoard: AICBSE

### RESIDENCE ADDRESS

435, Street No-05 Surya Vihar, Part-III Near Mukul Builders, Faridabad, Haryana, 121013

#### PERSONAL INFORMATION

• Father's Name: Sri Leela Kant Jha

• Title: Global Mobility Advisor, Immigration Professional

Date of Birth: 02/12/96Nationality: IndianReligion: Hindu

### ADDITIONAL EDUCATION FEATURE

Well versed with computers. Knowledge about basic computer operations, Microsoft Office, internet.

### **DISCLAIMER**

I certify that the information given above is true to the best of my knowledge.

### **ACCOMPLISHMENTS**

• Achieve the goal of completing spinoff-related projects by effectively helping with handover and transition to moving team.